so we've established its authenticity
self honesty is very important Nessa
Nessa received sense of shame and a fear
of wrongdoing
perhaps the Buddha says you know the
guardians of goddess
what a sense of shame fear wrongdoing
and guilt his guilt the same he can be
yeah sure because it's yeah cuz you I
think he probably would be on the same
level exactly but why is a sense of shame well
exactly but why is a sense of shame well
because he prevents you from doing bad
is if you don't have that preventing you
in it sure is nothing stopping so that's
why it's good to have a sense of shame
even if you don't necessarily have
wisdom or restraint in place in these
that sense of shame keep you from
becoming an animal in terms of your
behavior so that's why it's the guardian
of the world as the Buddha said if there
were no sense of shame the sons will be
sleeping with mothers and sisters and
fathers with daughters he would just be
like animal around for long so there is
that just that like even for a
completely unenlightened mind the sense
of shame at least is something they
would now obviously have the other
extreme of you know when people become
religious in any tents that turn into
this like a moral Commandments in the
repression but that's not anymore that
sense of shame it or that you know when
you're ashamed of everything with
anything they're not shameful but it's
this kind of natural sense of shame in
regard to you know nudity
or the exposure or like fluid cause
things in general so with that sense of
shame there is at least some kind of
rules so to speak in the world that
natural level because otherwise
everybody
to decline meant to read heaven for most
people as well as a human thing you have
beginning parent since I'm sure he
exactly feel when you're doing something
wrong yeah that's exactly what it is you
have to be unsteady yeah if you're
honest if you're authentic and cell
phone it's that sense of shame that's
exactly what becomes what reveals itself
I'm not talking about the fabricated so
I call it a shameful but it's really
just kind of more like a hateful
attitude that people turn into like that
they can't morally judgmental and so on
that's more just a common car wheel
wheel and repression no if you're
authentic then exactly there are things
that you don't necessarily want to do
with others or or being like known which
means then because you're authentic you
wouldn't be doing it you're not going to
try to consume the time and in the same
sense the guilt for doing something
wrong yes then you realize instead of denying
yes then you realize instead of denying
it ignoring it as I don't hate yourself
and well no you accept the guilt as a
result of what you've done carelessly
and the next time it will make you think
twice because you're not running away
from the disagreeable feeling of the
guilt you're accepting it and sometimes
it can endure for days and then come
back again and again and again each time
it comes
each time you accepted this issue these
thoughts me
it's good to be guilt-free no sure
that's true it's good to be guilt-free
and the only way to be guilt-free is
fully accepting guilt and then going
beyond it not by ignoring it or denying
it
and that that that is exactly the case
people feel that inherent sense of shame
but they project it and blame society
for it I mean yes Society has a lot to
plain the degree of shaming but there is
that threshold which is the natural
shame and some people yet you have more
of it some people have less of it
certain things they will just make you
uncomfortable but then people find that a problem
but then people find that a problem
because yeah it can be unpleasant
obviously it's preventing you from doing
what you want to do and then yeah you do
blame society you bring the culture you
rebel against it you go completely you
try to override it but that's that's
completely misplaced effort but referees
actually know there is a place for that
natural degree of sense of shame in
regard to doing things that are
really nice
inappropriate because of that and the
fear of wrongdoing that way it's always
bound together oh I don't want to do it
but stealing learning stealing lying
cheating yeah just being basically
acting like that like a just following
your desires in the same manner an
animal would without any reflection or
you know you see dogs I mean they get
into they get you into village and they
know they're most likely gonna be
attacked and maybe seriously injured by
all the other pack dogs but they just
they just saw either a female and lost
perspective or food and lost perspective
and you know how they know how it's
gonna end but they just have no
reflection over it to consider it so
they just go and eat and while they then
they get attacked and that's it there is
some tree consequences exactly
discontinuity they they come back to the
menu because the mind doesn't doesn't
possess the same powers of reflection as
human mind does and that's why they
don't have the sense of shame that's why
you know you have a puppy and the mother
and it's all now that's been murder but
once it passed a certain age and he
starts responding to female hormones and
in adolescence security then he just
starts seeing the mother as a female
it's not anymore
as a mother for as long as you know the
heat is going on there's no sense shame
they don't receive that but for most
people they do they do have that
recognition and that sense of shame with
regarding becoming self transparent by
keeping your desires in check then you
realize that with or without the sense
of shame you are the one responsible for
saying yes to desires and following them
through because doesn't matter what what
thoughts your mind might be presenting
in from the desire possibilities for
things you want to do that doesn't
matter what matters is you accept it or
not and then following through in doing
so that self-honesty self-honesty you
don't blame the society doubling
government you don't blame your genes or
that's how it's born
because even if all those things are in
play you in the present moment is always
responsible are always responsible
selection the consequences yeah
well that can help but not necessarily
it's like same you know people try to
give up some addiction they can reflect
on consequences but when the addiction
present agency consequences relevant on
the same level as well the addiction is
but if yourself honest you realize you
would be able to allow whatever pressing
desire arises you would be allowed to
arise and have enough space to not give
it in
but that takes that you have to start
seeing benefit even in that initial
restraint if you don't then there is no
there won't be enough
well the one bit of ground for and
without that restraint beforehand you
you won't be able to allow desire to
come close without you acting upon it
it's only succumbing you'll be
but the restrain we prevent it does
means gonna make things well it will
make things nicer and easier and more
peaceful later on the mind that grows
out of it but we rose from it but until
then it's actually yeah it's going to
reveal the paint underlying pain beneath
the desire and the lack of restraint